Guide to the Harriot Stanton Blatch Papers, 1807-1936 (bulk 1908-1920)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Harriot Stanton Blatch Papers,
1807-1936
1908-1920
Blatch, Harriot Stanton, 1856-1940
2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, clippings, ephemera, speeches, manuscripts and research materials relating to Blatch's involvment in the suffrage movement.
Biographical Note
Harriot Stanton Blatch was born Harriot Eaton Stanton on January 20, 1856 in Seneca Falls, New York. Her father, Henry Brewster Stanton was a lawyer, New York state senator, and abolitionist. Her mother, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, was a leader in the women's rights movement. Harriot graduated from Vassar College in 1878. She met William Henry Blatch, an English businessman, in 1881. They married in 1882 and lived in England until 1902, when she and her family moved to the United States.
Blatch was active in women's groups and social reform organizations in England, and is credited with revitalizing the American woman suffrage movement upon her return to New York. She established the Equality League of Self-Supporting Women, later renamed the Women's Political Union (WPU). The WPU stressed the involvement of working women in the suffrage movement and connected women's rights with trade unionism. Under her leadership the WPU held many outside forums and organized the first of many suffrage parades in 1910. They also testified at legislative hearings, lobbied, and oversaw polling activities.
Harriot Stanton Blatch was also active in other peace and social justice movements and was a strong advocate for legislation regarding workers' and children's rights
Chronology
1856 Born Harriot Eaton Stanton in Seneca Falls, New York
1878 Graduated from Vassar College
1882 Married William Henry Blatch
1894 Awarded M.A. from Vassar College
1902 Returned to the United States after living in England for 20 years
1907 Founded the Equality League of Self-Supporting Women
1910 The Equality League of Self-Supporting Women renamed the Women's Political Union
1918 Published Mobilizing Woman-Power
1920 Published A Woman's Point of View
1940 Died in Greenwich, Connecticut
Scope and Content Note
The Harriot Stanton Blatch collection consists of correspondence, clippings, reports, speeches, notes, and ephemera that document the suffrage movement. Much of the collection relates to the activities of Blatch and the Women’s Political Union (formerly the League of Self-Supporting Women) in New York State. These activities include lobbying, campaigning, organizing parades, and poll watching. The collection also contains some material pertaining to suffrage activities at the national level, specifically during the 1916 presidential campaign. A significant portion of correspondence contained in the collection is between Blatch and Caroline Lexow. This collection of materials was assembled and used by Blatch to prepare her books on women’s suffrage, and both hand-written and typed portions of her manuscripts are scattered throughout the collection.
Also included in the collection is material pertaining to Blatch’s later work on factory legislation, the minimum wage, and other labor issues.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Blatch, Harriot Stanton, 1856-1940; Babcock, Caroline L. (Caroline Lexow), b. 1882; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902; Beard, Mary Ritter, 1876-1958; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947; De Forest, Nora Blatch; Pankhurst, E. Sylvia (Estelle Sylvia), 1882-1960; Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928
Organizations:
Equality League of Self-Supporting Women (New York, N.Y.); Women's Political Union (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Women--Suffrage--New York (State)--History; Suffrage--New York (State)--Legislative history; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--20th century
Document Types:
Diaries
VCL Categories
Politics; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Jennifer Palmentiero, March 2007
Acquisition Information
On deposit from Coline Jenkins-Sahlin.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically. The original order of the materials within the folders was not altered, however the folders were rearranged by date. The dates reflect materials about that time period, not necessarily materials created during that time. Dates in quotation marks were transcribed from the original folders.
Container List
- "Before 1907" — Includes account of time at Vassar (Folder 1.1)
- "1907-1908" — Includes Hoffman House lawsuit, League of Self-Supporting Women, New York legislative work (Folder 1.2)
- "1908" — Includes Women's Political Union (Folder 1.3)
- 1908 — Text of speech "The Event We Celebrate, Nov. 12, 1908" (Folder 1.4)
- 1908 — Text of speech about Elizabeth Cady Stanton (Folder 1.5)
- 1908 — Text of speech presented on Oct. 16, 1908 (Folder 1.6)
- 1909 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.7)
- 1909-1914 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.8)
- 1910 — Includes first suffrage parade, campaign activities, and legislative activities (Folder 1.9)
- 1910 — Includes National American Women's Suffrage Association, Equal Franchise Society, and Women's Political Union (Folder 1.10)
- 1910 — Correspondence from Blatch to Caroline Lexow (Folder 1.11)
- "1912 Clippings" — Clippings dated 1910-1912 (Folder 1.12)
- "1911 Pankhurst Parade, March in Albany, Legislature" (Folder 1.13)
- "1911 Clippings" (Folder 1.14)
- 1911-1912 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.15)
- 1911-1913 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.16)
- "1912" — Includes manuscript and related research materials (Folder 1.17)
- "1913" — Includes suffrage parade (Folder 1.18)
- 1913 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.19)
- 1913 — Caroline Lexow correspondence (Folder 1.20)
- 1913 — Includes parade on Wall Street (Folder 1.21)
- "1913" — Manuscripts (Folder 1.22)
- 1914 — Includes Republican Convention and Constitutional Convention (Folder 1.23)
- "1914" — Manuscripts (Folder 1.24)
- "1914 material" — Includes Caroline Lexow correspondence (Folder 1.25)
- 1914 — Includes Caroline Lexow Correspondence (Folder 1.26)
- 1914 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.27)
- 1914 — Includes Caroline Lexow correspondence and reports (Folder 1.28)
- 1914 — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.29)
- 1915 — Includes text of speech (Folder 1.30)
- 1915 — Manuscripts (Folder 1.31)
- "1916" — Federal election (Folder 1.32)
- 1916 — Federal election (Folder 1.33)
- 1916 — "Presidential Suffrage" (Folder 1.34)
- "1917" — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.35)
- 1919 — Includes correspondence from Blatch to Nora Blatch De Forest (Folder 1.36)
- 1923-1933 — "Protective Legislation" — factory legislation, minimum wage, Equal Rights Amendment, child labor (Folder 1.37)
- 1929 — Correspondence from Blatch to Nora Blatch De Forest (Folder 1.38)
- 1929-1936 — Includes materials about Elizabeth Cady Stanton (Folder 1.39)
- 1933 — Includes National Council of Women (Folder 1.40)
- 1933 — Rollins College memorial to Elizabeth Cady Stanton (Folder 1.41)
- 1934 "Partial contents of first black letter box" — includes Equal Rights Amendment (Folder 1.42)
- 1936 "Press Clippings" (Folder 2.1)
- 1936 — Blatch's "80th Birthday Jan. 20, 1936" (Folder 2.2)
- 1920s, 1930s — Miscellaneous (Folder 2.3)
- 1920s, 1930s — Miscellaneous (Folder 2.4)
- 1920s, 1930s — "After Suffrage" (Folder 2.5)
- 1930s — "Miscellaneous" (Folder 2.6)
- 1930s correspondence — Letters worth notice: Mary Beard, Adelaede Johnson, Carrie Chapman Catt (Folder 2.7)
- 1930s — "Beard Correspondence" (Folder 2.8)
- "Partial contents of first black letter box" — Journals (Folder 2.9)
- "Demonstrations, Torch, Fairs, Van, Art Exhibit" — Manuscripts (Folder 2.10)
- "War, Mobilizing Women Power" — Includes research materials (Folder 2.11)
- "Blatch Notes" — Research materials (Folder 2.12)
- "Outlines" — Research materials (Folder 2.13)
- Clippings — Harriot Stanton Blatch denied U.S. citizenship (Folder 2.14)
- Elizabeth Cady Stanton’s death; women in Nazi Germany (Folder 2.15)
- Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Harriot Stanton Blatch – Includes brochures, clippings, correspondence (Folder 2.16)
- "Book" — Includes "Katy did" by Elizabeth Cady Stanton 11 March 1893, Seneca Falls tablet, Woman's Journal 60th anniversary (Folder 2.17)
- Encyclopedia of Social Sciences entries for Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony (Folder 2.18)
- Pamphlets — 1807-1911 (Folder 2.19)
- "Rare Pamplets" — 1892-1908 (Folder 2.20)
- "Partial contents of third letter box" — booklets and pamphlets 1891-1934 (Folder 2.21)
- Miscellaneous — includes copy of "Communist Manifesto" (Folder 2.22)
- Miscellaneous — contents of "second black letter box" (Folder 2.23)
- "Suffrage Cartoons" (Folder 2.24)
- New York State legislative debates, 1910, 1912 (Folder 2.25)
- New York State legislative debates, 1910-1914 (Folder 2.26)
- New York State legislative resolutions, 1910-1915 (Folder 2.27)
- Maps of New York senate districts (Folder 2.28)
- Miscellaneous correspondence — 1912-1918, 1930-1936, n.d. (Folder 2.29)
- Miscellaneous (Folders 2.30 - 2.33)
- Photograph of Susan B. Anthony (Folder 2.34)